A Guide to the Publications of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1947-1997
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Separate Publications
  - Bristol, Roger Pattrell. Index to Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1971. [10], 191 pp., 1971.1
    [1970.2] which might appear in some bibliographical journal, this volume completes the author's efforts on behalf of American printing before 1801." Composition and presswork by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa. 1492 copies.
  - Cauthen, Irby B., Jr., ed. Two Mementoes from the Poe-Ingram Collection: An Anniversary Keepsake for Members of The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia 1946-1971. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1971. [4] pp., 2 facsimiles, in folder., 1971.2
    Issued in celebration of the Society's twenty-fifth anniversary. Designed by Edward G. Foss at University Press of Virginia. "
    Two Mementoes from the Poe-Ingram Collection
    was composed by The Stinehour Press, Lunenburg, Vermont, who also did the letterpress printing. The two facsimiles were printed by The Meriden Gravure Company, Meriden, Connecticut. The paper for the commentary is Mohawk Superfine, and that used for the facsimiles is Bodleian White. The outside folder is Fabriano Cover. The types are Bembo for the text and Castellar for the initial letter. Of an edition of fifteen hundred, one thousand numbered copies have been reserved for the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia." Selected for the "Virginia Designers 1972" show at the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.
  - Beasley, Jerry C. A Check List of Prose Fiction Published in England 1740-1749. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1972. xiv, [4], 213 pp., 1972.1
    500 copies.
  - Bloomfield, B. C., and Edward Mendelson. W. H. Auden: A Bibliography 1924-1969. 2nd ed. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1972. xvi, 420 pp., 1972.2
    was composed, printed, and bound by Kingsport Press, Inc., Kingsport, Tennessee. The types are Janson and Garamond Bold and the paper is Warren's Olde Style. Design is by Edward G. Foss." For first edition see 1964.1. 2040 copies.
  - Herring, Phillip F., ed. Joyce's Ulysses Notesheets in the British Museum. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1972. viii, [6], 545 pp., 1972.3
    Dust jacket. Composition and presswork by the Stinehour Press. 1504 copies.
  - Howard-Hill, T. H. Ralph Crane and Some Shakespeare First Folio Comedies. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1972. xvi, [2], 190 pp., 1972.4
    495 copies.
  - Huss, Richard E. The Development of Printers' Mechanical Typesetting Methods 1822-1925. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1973. [12], 307 pp., 1973.1
    The Development of Printers' Mechanical Typesetting Methods, 1822-1925
    was composed, printed, and bound by Rose Printing Company, Inc., Tallahassee, Florida | The paper is Lockhaven Eggshell, No. 1033, and the type is Janson." 1045 copies.
  - Roth, Barry, and Joel Weinsheimer. An Annotated Bibliography of Jane Austen Studies 1952-1972. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1973. ix, [5], 272 pp., 1973.2
    779 copies.
  - Dameron, J. Lasley, and Irby B. Cauthen, Jr. Edgar Allan Poe: A Bibliography of Criticism 1827-1967. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1974. xvi, 386 pp., 1974.1
    Composition, presswork, and binding by Kingsport Press, Kingsport, Tenn. "A John Cook Wyllie Memorial Publication." 1629 copies.
  - Bowers, Fredson. Essays in Bibliography, Text, and Editing. Foreword by Irby B. Cauthen, Jr. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1975. viii, 550 pp., 1975.1
    1088 copies.
  - Fadiman, Regina K. Faulkner's Light in August: A Description and Interpretation of the Revisions. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1975. x, [6], 231 pp., 1975.2
    Composition by Sandra Anderson, Buffalo, N.Y.; presswork by Valley Offset, Deposit, N.Y. 1000 copies.
  - Faulkner, William. The Marionette s. [Charlottesville]: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, [1975]., 1975.3
    Six unbound, unopened gatherings of 8 leaves in portfolio within slipcase. A facsimile "Published by the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and the University Press of Virginia in memory of Linton R. Massey." "Type for
    The Marionettes
    was hand-set at the Alderman Press, University of Virginia Library, in Centaur and Arrighi. The work was printed on Arches paper by the Garamond Press, Baltimore, Maryland, in June, 1975, in an edition limited to one hundred numbered copies and twenty-six copies, hors commerce, lettered A through Z." 130 copies. For trade edition see 1977.1.
  - Partridge, A. C. A Substantive Grammar of Shakespeare's Nondramatic Texts. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1976. ix, [5], 232 pp., 1976.1
    715 copies.
  - Tarr, Rodger L. Thomas Carlyle: A Bibliography of English-Language Criticism, 1824-1974. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1976. xi, [3], 295 pp., 1976.2
    534 copies.
  - Faulkner, William. The Marionettes. Introduction and Textual Apparatus by Noel Polk. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1977. xxxii, 106 pp., 1977.1
    Dust jacket. Presswork (including jacket) by Payne Printery, Dallas, Pa. Binding by American Graphics, Philadelphia. "A Linton R. Massey Memorial Publication." Trade edition of 1975.3, with introduction and notes added. 1499 copies.
  - Herring, Phillip, ed. Joyce's Notes and Early Drafts for Ulysses: Selections from the Buffalo Collection. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1977. xii, 275 pp., 1977.2
    Composition and presswork by Stinehour Press, Lunenburg, Vt.; binding by American Graphics, Philadelphia. 1022 copies.
  - Blehl, Vincent Ferrer. John Henry Newman: A Bibliographical Catalogue of His Writings. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1978. xl, [2], 148 pp., 1978.1
    Composition by Sandra Anderson, Cos Cob, Conn.; presswork by Valley Offset, Deposit, N.Y. 752 copies.
  - Maynard, Joe, and Barry Miles. William S. Burroughs: A Bibliography, 1953-73. Foreword by William S. Burroughs. Introduction by Allen Ginsberg. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, [1978]. xxiii, [3], 242 pp., 1978.2
    Composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga.; presswork and binding by Fairfield Graphics, Fairfield, Pa. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 1968 copies, 50 signed by Burroughs.
  - Spalek, John M., in collaboration with Adrienne Ash and Sandra H. Hawrylchak. Guide to the Archival Materials of the German-Speaking Emigration to the United States after 1933 / Verzeichnis der Quellen und Materialien der deutschsprachigen Emigration in den U.S.A. seit 1933. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1978. xxv, [3], 1133 pp., 1978.3
    "The photo-ready copy of the manuscript was prepared by Marcella Curtright of Carson, California." Composition and presswork by Kingsport Press, Kingsport, Tenn.; binding by Carolina Ruling and Binding, Charlotte, N.C. 712 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. The Editing of Historical Documents. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, [1978]. 56 pp., 1978.4
    31 (1978)," 1-56. Presswork by Valley Offset, Deposit, N.Y, ?500 copies.
  - Hamblin, Robert W., and Louis Daniel Brodsky. Selections from the William Faulkner Collection of Louis Daniel Brodsky: A Descriptive Catalogue. Charlottesville: For Southeast Missouri State University and Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1979. xx, 171 pp., 1979.1
    Dust jacket. Composition by York Graphic Services, York, Pa.; presswork and binding by Murray Printing, Westford, Mass. 1059 copies.
  - Hodnett, Edward. Aesop in England: The Transmission of Motifs in Seventeenth-Century Illustrations of Aesop's Fables. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1979. x, 163 pp., 1979.2
    Composition and presswork by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa.; binding by Arnold's Book Bindery, Reading, Pa. Selected for the Neographics `80 Gold Award and display at the Franklin Institute, Philadelphia. 773 copies.
  - Ross, Charles L. The Composition of The Rainbow and Women in Love: A History. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1979. x, 168 pp., 1979.3
    Dust jacket, printed by Wayside Press, Charlottesville. Composition by Pub Press Sales, Baltimore, Md.; presswork by Murray Printing, Westford, Mass. 1049 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. Selected Studies in Bibliography. Foreword by Fredson Bowers [signed as "The Council of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia"]. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1979. [12], 506 pp., 1979.4
    Extra unpaginated leaf issued for insertion after p. 138. New composition by Heritage Printers, Charlotte, N.C.; presswork by Valley Offset, Deposit, N.Y. "The eleven most significant of these [articles by Tanselle in
    ], of his own choice, have now been collected at the initiative of the Society and reproduced by offset as they were originally printed." 842 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. VI, Part i: Introduction to the Smock Alley Othello; Collations. Part ii: Text of the Smock Alley Othello. Charlottesville: A Publication of Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia | University Press of Virginia, 1980. [4], 36; [24] pp., 1980.1
    Two parts bound together. Presswork and binding by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa. For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2. 442 copies.
  - Guiliano, Edward. Lewis Carroll: An Annotated International Bibliography 1960-1977. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and the Lewis Carroll Society of North America by University Press of Virginia, 1980. viii, [2], 253 pp., 1980.2
    Dust jacket. Composition by P & M Typesetting, Waterbury, Conn.; presswork (including jacket) and binding by Braun-Brumfield, Ann Arbor, Mich. 1507 copies; an additional 501 copies simultaneously printed for publication by Harvester Press in Brighton, England, 1981.
  - Life, Page West. Sir Thomas Malory and the Morte Darthur: A Survey of Scholarship and Annotated Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1980. xiii, [5], 297 pp., 1980.3
    Presswork by Vail-Ballou Press, Binghamton, N.Y. 824 copies.
  - MacMahon, Candace W. Elizabeth Bishop: A Bibliography 1927- 1979. Foreword by Elizabeth Bishop. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1980. xviii, [2], 227 pp., 1980.4
    Dust jacket, with blurb from
    Library Journal
    . Composition by Charma Press, Emeryville, Calif.; presswork (including jacket) and binding by Vail-Ballou Press, Binghamton, N.Y. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 1060 copies.
  - Grimshaw, James A., Jr. Robert Penn Warren: A Descriptive Bibliography, 1922-79. Foreword by Robert Penn Warren. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1981. xxiii, [1], 494 pp., 1981.1
    Dust jacket. Presswork (including jacket) and binding by Vail-Ballou Press, Binghamton, N.Y. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 1773 copies.
  - Weisenfarth, Joseph, ed. George Eliot: A Writer's Notebook, 1854- 1879, and Uncollected Writings. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1981. xli, [1], 301 pp., 1981.2
    Composition by Boro Typographers, New York, N.Y.; presswork and binding by Vail-Ballou Press, Binghamton, N.Y. 793 copies. Second printing 1984 by Thomson-Shore, Inc., Dexter, Mich. 264 copies.
  - Gallup, Donald. Ezra Pound: A Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and St. Paul's Bibliographies by University Press of Virginia, 1983. xiv, 548 pp., 1983.1
    Dust jacket, with blurb by Hugh Kenner. No. 7 in the St. Paul's Bibliographies series. Composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga. "The present work is a completely revised and updated edition of my
    A Bibliography of Ezra Pound
    (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1963)." 2234 copies.
  - Frost, Robert. Stories for Lesley, ed. Roger D. Sell. Illustrated by Warren Chappell. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1984. 77 pp., 1984.1
    Dust jacket. Composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga.; presswork (including jacket) and binding by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa. 1501 copies.
  - Pound, Ezra. A Quinzaine for This Yule. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1984. 27, [2] pp., 1984.2
    Self paper wrappers. Composition by Graphic Communications, Charlottesville; reproductions by University of Virginia Printing Services; presswork by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa.; handbinding by Mary Louise Ehrenpreis, Charlottesville. "This facsimile edition... [is] limited to 500 copies." 625 copies.
  - Roth, Barry. An Annotated Bibliography of Jane Austen Studies 1973- 83. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1985. xxi, [1], 359 pp., 1985.1
    Presswork and binding by Braun-Brumfield, Ann Arbor, Mich. 1035 copies.
  - Tucker, Edward L. The Shaping of Longfellow's John Endicott. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1985. liii, [1], 192 pp., 1985.2
    Dust jacket. Presswork (including jacket) and binding by Hamilton Printing, Rensselaer, N.Y. "Center for Scholarly Editions | An Approved Edition | Modern Language Association of America." 500 copies.
  - West, James L. W., III. A Sister Carrie Portfolio. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1985. vii, [1], 87 pp., 1985.3
    Dust jacket. Design by Angelica Design Group, N.Y., N.Y.; composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga.; presswork (including jacket) and binding by Braun-Brumfield, Ann Arbor, Mich. 793 copies.
  - Johnson, Linck C. Thoreau's Complex Weave: The Writing of A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers with the Text of the First Draft. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1986. xxi, [1], 490 pp., 1986.1
    Dust jacket, with blurb by Joel Myerson. 1745 copies.
  - Wright, Stuart. Randall Jarrell: A Descriptive Bibliography, 1929- 1983. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1986. xvi, 372 pp., 1986.2
    Dust jacket. Design by Diane Nelson, Charlottesville; composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga;, presswork (including jacket), and binding by Vail-Ballou Press, Binghamton, N.Y. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 1027 copies.
  - Wright, Stuart, and James L. W. West III. Reynolds Price: A Bibliography 1949-1984. Foreword by Reynolds Price. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1986. xiv, [2], 122 pp., 1986.3
    Dust jacket, with blurb by George Core,
    Sewanee Review
    . Composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga.; presswork and binding by Arcata Graphics Kingsport, Kingsport, Tenn. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 942 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. Textual Criticism since Greg: A Chronicle, 1950-1985. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1987. ix, [3], 154 pp., 1987.1
    Paper wrappers, with blurbs by Fredson Bowers, Don L. Cook, and Elizabeth Hall Witherell. "The three essays in this volume are reprinted here directly from the pages of
    , where they appeared in 1975 (28: 167-229), 1981 (34: 23-65), and 1986 (39: 1-46)." 1061 copies.
  - Wright, Stuart. Peter Taylor: A Descriptive Bibliography 1934- 87. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1988. xi, [1], 228., 1988.1
    Dust jacket, with blurb by George Garrett. Composition by Graphic Composition, Athens, Ga.; presswork by Thomson-Shore, Dexter, Mich. "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 783 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. VII, Part i: Introduction to the Smock Alley A Midsummer Night's Dream; Collations. Part ii: Text of the Smock Alley A Midsummer Night's Dream. Charlottesville: A Publication of Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia | University Press of Virginia, 1989. [4], 53; [20] pp., 1989.1
    Two parts bound together. "
    The Smock Alley
    A Midsummer Night's Dream
    Prompt-Book
    was composed in Linotype Baskerville and Monotype Goudy Old Style by Heritage Printers, Charlotte, N.C. It was printed by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa. and bound by Hoster Bindery, Hatboro, Pa." Selected for the NEO 1990 award (Philadelphia). For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2. 435 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. Textual Criticism and Scholarly Editing. Charlottesville & London: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1990. xiv, 353 pp., 1990.1
    "This volume brings together eight essays on textual criticism and scholarly editing... published between 1971 and 1983." New composition by Heritage Printers, Charlotte, N.C.; presswork and binding by Malloy Lithographing, Ann Arbor, Mich. 643 copies. Second printing 1993, 286 copies.
  - Vander Meulen, David L. Pope's Dunciad of 1728: A History and Facsimile. Foreword by Lola L. Szladits. Charlottesville & London: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and The New York Public Library by University Press of Virginia, 1991. xvii, [1], 174 pp., 1991.1
    "Typography, decorations, and binding design by Warren Chappell | Composition by Graphic Composition of Athens, Georgia | Printing by Malloy Lithographing, Inc., Ann Arbor, Michigan | Binding by John Dekker & Sons, Inc., Grand Rapids, Michigan." Selected for the 1992 Book, Jacket, and Journal Show of the Association of American University Presses. 754 copies.
  - Boughn, Michael. H.D.: A Bibliography 1905-1990. Charlottesville & London: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1993. ix, [1], 229 pp., 1993.1
    Dust jacket; "Jacket design by Anne Dutlinger." "A Linton R. Massey Descriptive Bibliography." 681 copies. $39.50.
  - Eddy, Donald D., and J. D. Fleeman. A Preliminary Handlist of Books to which Dr. Samuel Johnson Subscribed. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1993. [4], 34 pp., 1993.2
    Stiff paper wrappers. Occasional Publication No. 2. Reprinted from
    46 (1993), 186-220. "300 copies printed by Heritage Printers, Inc., Charlotte, North Carolina." 306 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. The Life and Work of Fredson Bowers. Foreword by David L. Vander Meulen. Checklist and Chronology by Martin C. Battestin. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1993. viii, 210 pp., 1993.3
    Occasional Publication No. 1. Reprinted from
    46 (1993), 1-186, with Foreword and Index (by Tanselle) added. "400 copies printed by Heritage Printers, Inc., Charlotte, North Carolina, of which 200 are reserved for the family and friends of Fredson Bowers and 200 are for sale by The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, Alderman Library, Charlottesville, VA 22903." 406 copies.
  - Vander Meulen, David L., and G. Thomas Tanselle, eds. Samuel Johnson's Translation of Sallust: A Facsimile and Transcription of the Hyde Manuscript. New York: The Johnsonians; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1993. vi, 40, [2] pp., 1993.4
    "This booklet is the forty-eighth annual keepsake of The Johnsonians and the third in a series of occasional publications issued by The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia. It was distributed at the dinner of The Johnsonians commemorating Samuel Johnson's 284th birthday, held at the Grolier Club, New York City, on 17 September 1993, with G. Thomas Tanselle in the chair and David L. Vander Meulen speaking on `Johnson's Translation of Sallust.'" "750 copies printed at The Stinehour Press, Lunenburg, Vermont, of which 250 are reserved for The Johnsonians and 500 are for sale by The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, Alderman Library, Charlottesville, VA 22903." 900 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. VIII: King Lear, Henry VIII, The Merry Wives of Windsor, Twelfth Night, The Comedy of Errors, The Winter's Tale. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1996. vi, 94, [1] pp., 1996.1
    Composition and presswork by Heritage Printers, Charlotte, N.C. The final volume of a series begun with 1960.2 (see description there); for electronic edition see 1997.2. 306 copies.
  - Ribble, Frederick G., and Anne G. Ribble. Fielding's Library: An Annotated Catalogue. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1996. lxxxv, [1], 435 pp., 1996.2
    Presswork and binding by Integrated Book Technology, Troy, N.Y. 322 copies.
  - Studies in Bibliography Cumulative Table of Contents. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, distributed electronically by University of Virginia Electronic Text Center, March 1996., 1996.3
    Searchable electronic index of authors and titles from
    1-49, encoded in TEI-conformant SGML. Keyboarding by David L. Gants (vols. 1-44) and Elizabeth K. Lynch (vols. 45-50); scanning and proofing by David L. Gants and Jessamy Town.
  - Studies in Bibliography Volume 7, ed. Fredson Bowers. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, distributed electronically by University of Virginia Electronic Text Center, March 1996., 1996.4
    Searchable electronic edition of
    7, encoded in TEI-conformant SGML. Scanning and proofing by Jennifer Hanna, Jessamy Town, and Stephen Welch; encoding by David L. Gants. Volume subsequently incorporated into 1997.3.